so since last time, okay, welcome back,
thank you for being here.
Last time Yann was using the tablet,
right? and how can you use the tablet and I
don't use the tablet, right? So I should
be as cool as Yann at least I think.
One more thing to begin with, there is a
spreadsheet where you can decide whether
you'd like to join the Slack channel
where we collaborate over making
some drawings for the website, fixing
some mathematical notations, having some
kind of, you know, fixing the error in
English in the English grammar or
whatever, so if you if you're interested
in helping in improving the content of
this class, feel free to fill out the
spreadsheet, okay? We are already a few of
us on the Slack channel, so I mean, if you
want to join, you're welcome. So
instead of writing on the whiteboard
because it's impossible to see I think
from the upper side we're gonna be going
to experiment with a new toy here. All
right.
First time, so you know, I'm a little bit
tense. Last time I screw up with a
notebook, so okay, alright. So we're gonna
be starting with a small review
about linear algebra. I hope I'm not
offending anyone, I'm aware that you
already taken linear algebra and you're
very strong in it but nevertheless I'd
like to provide you my intuition, my
perspective, okay? it's just one
slide, not too much, so maybe you'd like
to take out some paper and pen or you
can just you know, whatever, follow along.
So this one is going to be
linear algebra review.
Okay. Am I waiting a little bit? Let me
wait for a sec. Ready?? Yes? No? shake your
head. Okay fantastic, alright so we were
talking last time we had a neural
network with the input on the bottom
then we had an affine
transformation, then we have a hidden
layer right. So I'm gonna just write the
first equation. We're gonna have that my
hidden layer, and since I'm writing
with a pen, can you see anything? yeah?
so since I'm writing with a pen I'm
going to be putting a underscore
underneath the variable in order to
indicate it's a vector. Okay? that's how I
write vectors. So my H is gonna be a
nonlinear function f applied to my z and
z is going to be my linear input,
the output of the
affine transformation, so in this case
I'm gonna be writing here z is going to
be equal to my matrix A times x. We
can imagine there is no bias in this
case, it's generic enough because we can
include it bias inside the matrix and
have the first item of the x equal to
1. So if this x here belongs to R n and this
z here belongs to R m, first question:
what is the size of this matrix? Okay,
fantastic, so this matrix here is
gonna be our m times n, you have as many
rows as the dimension where you shoot to
and you have as many columns as the
dimension where you're shooting from, ok?
All right so let's expand this one,
so this matrix here is gonna be equal to
what do you have a_ a_ so on until
the last one, which is gonna be? shout.
Thank you, 1...?
yeah 1 n then you have second one's
gonna have a_ a_ so on until the
last one which is a, right? and then you
keep going down until the last one which
is going to be? what are the indexes? m 1,
right? Okay so you have a_, a_ and
so on until a_, okay thank you.
And then we have here our x, right?
so you have x_1, x_2 and so on until x_n,
right?
You're more responsive than last year,
good, thank you. Alright, so we can also
rewrite this one in different ways. So
the first way I'm gonna write this one
is gonna be the following, so I'm gonna
have here these a 1 then I'm gonna have
here my a 2 and then I have the last one
which is gonna be my a n, ok? and then
here I'm gonna be multiplying this by a
column vector, right? so my column vector
I'm gonna be write it like this.
Alright, so what is the output of this operation?
so these are metrics, you have a vector,
the outcome is going to be a? vector. So
what is gonna be the first item of my
vector? I don't use dots because I'm not
a physicist, actually I am but we are
doing linear algebra, so what should I
write?
Alright, so that's already transpose
because those are a row vector so I just
write a I'm gonna just mean just right
right so I have a 1 x ok so there is no
transposition here, no dots around and so
on. Second element is gonna be? a 2, okay,
x and then until the last one which is
gonna be? okay, there's no dot but sure.
Like someone is calling that dot product
instead of the cross product but that is
assumes like you use a different kind of
notation.
All right so and this is gonna be my, so
how many elements does this vector have?
m okay so we have z 1, z 2 and so on
until z m and this is my final set, right?
my vector z, okay? Fantastic. So now
we are going to be focusing a little bit
about the meaning of this thing over
here okay, other questions so far?
all right this is very trivial so far, I
hope, I mean let me know if if not, okay
so let's analyze one of these guys
here so I'd like to figure out what is
the meaning of writing a T times x right
so my a T is gonna be my generic a i so
let's assume in this case when n equals 2
okay? So what is a T x? so a T x is going
to be equal to what? so let me draw here
something so that is gonna be easier for
you to understand. So this one is gonna
be my a, these gonna be my alpha and
then here you have like it's gonna be my
x and is this gonna be here my xi, so
what is the output of this
product here? This one here.
Say again, sorry. A transpose, let's
call it, let's say that is a row vector
Can you see? no? what is gonna be the
output of this operation here? no, why?
This is this is like a generic one of
the many a's, right? there are m a's,
this is one of those m a's, so I'm
multiplying one of those a's times my x
right let's assume there are only two
dimensions, so what is gonna be the
output of this scalar product? can
someone tell me? no no no like normal
scalar product. Hold on
so you have a here, you have
here this part here is gonna be a 1 it
is gonna be a 2 okay? then you have
here x 1 and now you have x 2, right? so how
do you express this scalar product here?
okay, so I'm just writing, let me know if
it's all clear, so I'm gonna write here:
a 1 times x 1 plus a 2 times x 2, right?
this is the definition. Clear, right? So
far, yeah? no? okay, yeah, question yeah. That
is meant to be a transpose. A row
times column vector so let's assume a is
a column vector then I have row times
column. So let's keep writing this
stuff here so what is a 1? how can I
compute a 1? Say again? ok ok.
So I'm gonna write here the a 1 is going
to be the length of vector a times
cosine alpha, then what about x 1? someone
else. The same right? No, wait, what? what
is x 1? same thing, right, different
letters. so someone say something. You're
following, you're completely confused,
you're not having any idea, it's too easy?
I have no idea what's going on here. It's
good right? so far ok? what's gonna be the
second term? This one is gonna be x
here, right? times cos xi right, and then you
had the second term which is going to be
what? magnitude of a... shout, I can't hear. Ok
sine of alpha and then
okay thank you okay
all right I'm gonna be just putting
together those two guys so you're gonna
get equal magnitude of a times magnitude
of x times cosine alpha cosine Xi plus
sine alpha and sine, cosine, sine Xi
I'm sorry.
what is the stuff in the parentheses? all
right so it's the cosine of the
difference of the two angle right?
everyone knows trigonometry here, right?
so, high school stuff so this one is
gonna be equal to a x times the cosine
of cos xi minus alpha, right? or the
other way around, alpha minus xi.
So what does this mean? You can think
about each element. so far is clear? I
didn't do any magic yeah shake your head
like this for yes, this for no, this
for maybe, no something's working. Okay so
you can think about whenever you
multiply a matrix times a vector that
basically each output of this operation
is gonna be measuring, so okay hold on,
what is this cosine? how much is cosine
of zero? One. So it means if these two
angles, if the two vectors are aligned,
which means there is a zero angle
between the two vectors you can have the
maximum value of this element, right?
whenever when you have the minus the
most negative value? when they are
opposite, right? so when they're in
opposition of phase you're gonna get the
most negative magnitude but then if you
apply just let's say a ReLU you're gonna cut
all those negative things you're just
checking for the positive matches right
so neural net basically just perhaps
is gonna be figuring out only the
positive matches, right? and so again when
you multiply a matrix times a column
vector you
be performing element-wise sorry scalar
product between each column each row of
the matrix which represents your kernel
right? so whenever you have like a linear
layer your kernel is gonna be the whole
row of the matrix and now you see what
is the projection of that input on that
column, I meant, on the input on that row
right? so each element of this product is
going to tell you the alignment with
which the input is what is the alignment
of the input with respect to the
specific row of the matrix okay?
yes? no? this should shape some more like
intuition while we are using these
linear transformations they are like
allowing you to see the projection of
the input onto different kind of
orientations let's say this way. okay? you
can try to you know extrapolate this in
high dimensions I guess the intuition at
least I can give it to you works
definitely in two and three dimensions,
in higher dimensions I kind of think it
works in a similar way. next lesson we
are going to watch we are actually we
are going to see how what is the
distribution of the projections in a
higher dimensional space is this sort
gonna be so cool I think. all right so
this was the first part of I think of
the class oh well there is one more more
part so actually here this z here we
can also write it in a different way so
maybe this is maybe it's known maybe
it's not known. when I saw it first time
I didn't know so you know it's it's cool
that sometimes you see these things once
again maybe so let's go back here is the
same z there there and so you can express
this z as being equal the vector a 1 in
this case a 1 is gonna be the first
column of the a matrix ok and this one
is going to be multiplied by the scalar
x1 now you have the second column of the
matrix so I have a 2 this is multiplied
by the second element of the X right
until the last one which is gonna be?
again? I can't hear if it's m or n? m? like
this? or n? you know sign language? which
one? n? right, you know sign language? no?
you should learn it's good, you know?
inclusivity. a n, right? so the last column
times your x n, of course because x
has a size of n, there are n items, right?
and so basically when you also when you
do a you know transformation a linear
or apply a linear operator you
are going to be basically weighting each column
of the matrix with the coefficient that
is in a, you know, you have first column
times the first coefficient of the
vector, second column, and by the second
item, plus third column times the third
item and so you can see the output of
this DN transformation is a weighted sum
of the columns of the a matrix okay? so
this is a different kind of intuition
sometimes you see these as like whenever
you want to express your signal your
data is a combination of different, you
know, the composition, this is kind of a
linear composition of your input. alright
so that was the first part it is the
recap about the linear algebra. a second
part is going to be something even more
cool I think. questions so far?
no? easy? too easy? you're getting bored?
sorry okay all right then I'm gonna
speed up I guess.
alright so let's see how we can extend
the one that the stuff we have seen
right now to convolutions right so maybe
convolution sometimes are a little bit
weird let's see how we can do an
extension to convolutions
all right. so let's say I start with the
same matrix. so I'm gonna have here four
rows and then three columns. okay. so my
data has to be? if I have, if I have this
matrix, if I multiply this to a column, my
column vector should be? of size? three,
thank you. all right so let me draw here
my column vector of size three and this
is gonna give you an output of size four
okay fantastic
but then is your data, let's say you're
gonna listen to some nice audio, audio
file, is your data just three sample long?
how long is gonna be your data? let's say
you listening to a piece of music that
is like three minutes
how many sample does three minutes of
audio have? yeah, I guess, what is
gonna be my sampling rate? let's say
twenty two, okay. twenty two thousand kilo
Hertz, right? 22 kilohertz so how many
samples three minutes of music have?
say again? you sure? is monophonic
or stereophonic? just kidding. okay so
you're gonna multiply the number of
samples, the number of seconds, right? the
number of seconds times the frame rate,
right? the okay, the frequency in this
case. anyhow so this signal is gonna be
very very long, right? it's gonna be keep
going down so if I have a vector that is
very very long I have I have to use a
matrix which is gonna be very very fat,
wide, right? okay fantastic so this top
keeps going this direction,
alright, so my question for you is gonna
be what should I put in this location
here?
what should I put here? so do we care
about things that are further away?
no, why not?
because our data has the property of
locality, fantastic. so what am I gonna go
what am I gonna be putting here? a big
zero, right, fantastic, well done, okay so we put
a zero here and then what is the other
property so let me start drawing this
stuff again right so can I have my
kernel of size three and then here I
have my data which is gonna be very long
right? and so on. Can't draw hold on. I can't see. All right so
here there are zero, then let's say what
is the other property my
natural data have? stationarity, which
means? the pattern that you expect to
find this can be kind of repeating over
and over again right? and so if I have
here my three values here perhaps I'd
like to reuse them over and over again
right? and so if these three values let
me change the color maybe so you can see
in there is the same stuff. so I have
three values here and then I'm gonna be
using these three same values one step
futher right? and I keep going further down
and I keep going this way all
right. So what should I put here on the
bottom? What should I put here? a zero,
right? why that why is that? because of
locality of the data. right? so putting
zeros around is called it's also called
padding but in this case it's called
sparsity, right? so this is like sparsity
and then the replication of this thing
that is over and over over again
it's called stationarity was the property
of the signal, this is called weight
sharing. yeah?
okay fantastic all right so how many how
many values do we have now? how many
parameters I have on the right hand side?
well so we have three parameters. Over
the left hand side instead we
had? Twelve, right? so is the right side
is gonna be, is the right side gonna
work at all? you have three parameters
one side on the other side you have 12.
Okay? that is good, using locality and
whatever not like sparsity
and parameter sharing but then we
end up with just three parameters, isn't
this too restrictive? how can we have
multiple multiple parameter? what's
missing here in the big picture? there
are multiple channels, right? so this is
just one layer here and then you have
this stuff coming out from the
board here, so you have the
first kernel down here, now you have some
second kernel let's say this one, and I
have last one here, right? and so you have
each plane of these metrics being
containing just one kernel which is
replicated multiple times. Who knows the
name of this matrix? so this is gonna
be called Toeplitz matrix
okay? so what is the main feature of
these Toeplitz matrix? what is the big
big big thing that you won't notice? it's
a sparse matrix. okay okay what is gonna
be here, this first item over here? what
is the content of the first guy? yeah? so
this one here is gonna be the extension
of my linear transformation which was,
you know, I have a signal that is longer
than three samples therefore I have to
make this matrix fatter, second part is
going to be given that I don't care about
what things, like, things that are here
down I don't care about things that are
here if I look at the points that are up
here, so gonna be putting a big 0 here
such that everything that is down
here, it gets cleaned up, right? and
finally I'm gonna be using the same
kernel over and over again because I
assume that my data is stationary and
therefore I assume that similar patterns
are gonna be happening over and over
again therefore I'm gonna be using this
one which is written here:
weight sharing.
Finally given that this one gives you
only three parameters to
work with I will use several layers in
order to have different, you know,
channels. So this one is one kernel.
before, one kernel was the whole row of
the matrix, okay? so when you have a fully
connected layer, the only difference
between a fully connected layer and a
convolution is that you have the full
row of the matrix. So what is gonna
be in this first item over here? anyone?
so the green kernel, let's call the
green kernel just a 1 let me actually
make it glow green because it's green
kernel. So you have a 1 times... what? it's
gonna be from the number one to number
three right? and then the second item is
gonna be same same dude here a 1 and
then you're gonna have the x shifted by
one and so on right? make sense? yeah and
then we're gonna have this one is going
to be the green output then you're gonna
have the blue output one layer coming
out and then you have the further one
the red one coming.
even one layer out. Okay? Was the
iPad experience cool?
yes? no? I liked it. Okay. Other questions?
say again? the blue circle this one? it's a
big zero
that's the sparsity one the same is here.
yes? no? yeah yeah.
so here I just put a lot of
zeros inside here so I killed all the
values that are away from the little
part and then I repeat the same three
values over and over again because I
expect to find the same pattern in
different regions of this, this big big
signal I have. This one here? So I said
that in this case I'm gonna have just
three values, right? and we started with
12 values and I ended up with 3 which is
really really little so if I'd like to
have let's say 6 values then if I want
to have six values and I can have my
second 3 on a different plane and I
perform the same operation whenever you
multiply this matrix times a vector you
perform a convolution so it just to tell
you that a convolution is just a matrix
multiplication with a lot of zeros
that's it. Yeah so they're gonna have
this one here, then you have a second one,
then you have a third one so you have three
versions of the input. Alright. So for the
second part of the class I'm gonna be
showing you some more interactive things
please do participate to the second part
as well alright? so let's try so I have
rebranded I have rebranded the website
and now the
environment is going to be called pDL
so PyTorch deep learning instead of
deep learning mini course, it was too
long. So let me start by running this one
so
PyTorch deep learning so we can do just
Conda activate activate PyTorch deep
learning (pDL) and then let's open notebook, the
Jupiter notebook. All right, so now you're
gonna be watching, going over the
listening to kernels. So I showed you a
convolution on paper well on my tablet
now you're going to be listening to
convolution so can such that you can
really appreciate what these convolutions
are. Here we said, the new kernel right
which is called pDL PyTorch deep
learning so you're gonna notice the same
kind of, you know, procedure if you update
your system. Alright so in this case we
can read the top here so let me hide the
top here.
Alright so given the assumption of
locality, stationarity, and
compositionality we can reduce the
amount of computation for a matrix
vector multiplication by using a sparse
because local Toeplitz matrix because
stationary scheme in this way we can
simply end up rediscovering the
convolution operator, alright? moreover, we
can also recall that a scalar product is
a simply a normalized cosine distance
which tells us the alignment of two
vectors,
more specifically we compute the
magnitude of the orthogonal projection
of two vectors onto the other and vice
versa.
So let's figure out now how all this
can make sense by using our ears, okay? so
i'm going to be importing a library that
professor here at NYU made and here I'm
gonna be just loading my audio data and
I'm gonna have that in my x, and then my
sampling rate is going to be
in the other variable. So here I'll just
show you I'm gonna have like 70,000
samples in this case because I have a
sampling rate of 22 kilo Hertz and then
my total time is gonna be three seconds,
okay, so three seconds times 22 you get
what? so it's not 180 you were saying, it
was a hundred and eighty, it was three, right?
oh it was three minutes, oh you're right
it's three seconds, so you actually are
correct my bad. So this is three seconds
so times 22 kilo Hertz you get 70
roughly some 70,000 samples. Here I'm
gonna be importing some libraries to
show you something and then I'm gonna be
showing you the first chart so this is
the audio signal I have imported right
now how does it look like? wavy, okay cool.
Can you tell me how it sounds?
Student: "aaaaaaaaaaahhhhhh".
That was a good guess. The guess was 'aaah'. Yeah, you can't tell exactly
what's the content, right? from
this diagram because the amplitude of,
the y-axis here is gonna be
showing you just the amplitude. can I
turn off the light? is it okay? or... are you
sure? okay thank you,
I really dislike these lights. Okay.
Goodnight. Oh see how nice it is? okay
cool. Alright so you can't tell anything
here right?
you cannot tell what is the what is
the sound, right? so how can we figure out
what is the sound inside here? so for
example I can show you a transcript of
the sound and, actually let me let me
actually force these in your in your
your head, right? so you're gonna have...
hold on, didn't work. *A sound comes on*
all right so now we actually heard it,
okay so now you can actually see *mimics the sound*
you know you can kind of
imagine a little bit but okay so what
notes did we play there? like how can I
figure out what are the notes that
they are inside? so I'm gonna be showing
this one, so since this is a bit brighter
I can see your faces. How many of you can
not read this? Oh, ouch…
Okay, so let me see if I can ask for some help.
Maybe someone can help us out here.
Okay. Let's see.
Hey, hey Alf!
Oh, hi Alf!
How's going?
Yeah, yeah, I'm fine, thank you.
Nice glasses there!
Oh, thank you for the glasses.
Oh, nice sweater! you too!
Nice sweater!
Oh, we're wearing the same sweater!
Can you help us out?
They don't know how to read the
Oh, the connection…
What the f- hell!
They cannot read the score!
Can you help us out, please?
Alright!
Let me try to help you out.
Thank you!
Let me switch the camera.
Alright.
Please, do.
So, here we can go like…
and hear first how it sounds everything.
So, it's going to be like that.
How cool is that?
*students clap*
Thank you. It took four
lessons for you to clap me. So now…
This is very nice of you. Let's keep
going.
A♭, then we have an E♭, and then a A♭.
The difference between the first A♭ and the other one in frequencies
is that the first A♭ is going to be twice the frequency as the other one.
And instead, in the middle, we have the 5th.
We're going to figure out what is the frequency of that.
And then, we are gonna be going to a B♭, here.
On the left hand side, instead, we have the accompagnement,
and so we're gonna have a A♭ and B♭
and then B♭ and E♭.
So, if we put all together, we gonna get
this one.
Alright? Simple, no?
Yep! Thank you!
Bye-bye!
Byeeeeee!
See? This took a whole damn day to
prepare…
I was so nervous before come here…
I didn't know if it actually would have worked…
Both of them, tablet and this one.
I'm so happy!
Now I can actually go to sleep, later.
Anyhow, so this was like in the first
part you're gonna have the first note,
there's A♭ that you have a B♭
A♭ and B♭ so you have *recreates the sound* and the and the
difference between the first pitch and
is one octave, therefore the first
frequency is gonna be twice the second
frequency. Okay? so whenever we're gonna
be observing the waveform one sign will
have a shorter like the half the
period of the other one, right?
especially the A♭ on top
is gonna have a period which is half of
the period of the A♭ on the bottom one,
right, so you have *recreates the sound* okay, if you go half of
this one you get *makes sound* right okay okay so how
do we actually get these notes out from
that spectra, from the waveform?
who can tell me how can I extract these
pitches, these frequencies from the other
signal? any guess? okay Fourier transform
that I think is kind of a good guess.
What happens if I perform now a
Fourier transform of that signal? anyone
can actually answer me? you cannot raise
your hand because I don't see, just shout.
So if you basically perform the Fourier
transform of the whole signal are you
going to hear *makes sound* like the whole notes together *makes sound*?
all together, right, but then you can't
figure out which pitch is playing where
or when actually in this case right.
Ha! So we need kind of a Fourier
transform which is localized and so a
localized Fourier transform in time or
in space depending on whatever domain
you are using its called spectrogram.
right, and so on I'm gonna be
printing for you the spectrogram, oh
sorry.
and I'll be printing here the
spectrogram of this one here. And so, here
you can compare the two, alright, on the
first part here on this side here you're
gonna have this peak here at 1600 which
is the *makes sound*, the pitch is actually higher. *makes sound* there we go. Now
you have a second one which is this peak
here *makes sound* and then this one *makes sound*. You can see this peak, right? And you
see this peak, yeah okay, so these peaks
are gonna be the actual notes I play
with the right hand,
so let's actually put those together and
I'm gonna have here the frequencies. So I
have 1600, 1200 and 800, can you see here?
I have 1600, 800, why is one double of
the other? because they are one octave
apart, so if this is *makes sound* this gonna be *makes sound* okay
and this is a fifth which also
has a nice interval. So let me actually
generate these signals here and then I
gotta be concatenate them all so I'm
gonna be playing both these. the first
one is actually the original audio, but
let me try again, whereas if I play
the second one, the concatenation, yeah so
it's a bit loud, I can now cannot even
reduce the volume. Oh I can reduce it
here. Too much. Okay, let me go again. All
right.
So this is the concatenation of these
four different pitches so guess what we
are going to be doing next? so how can I
extract all the notes that I can hear in
a specific given piece? so let's say
you play a full score and I'd like to
know which pitch is played at what time. Of
what? so the answer was convolution, just
for the recording, so I'm asking convolution
of what? no convolution of the spectrogram, so
you have convolution of your input
signal with what? with some different
kind of pitches right which pitches will
you pick? let's say you don't see the
spectrum because let's say I'm just gonna
play any kind of piece of music so I'd
like to know all possible notes they are
there, what would you do?
you don't know all pitches, how would you
try? right, so in which are all the
pitches you may want to use, if you're if
I'm playing the piano? all the keys of
the piano, right? so if I play a
concerto with the piano then I want to
have a piece of audio for each of
those keys and I'm gonna be running
convolutions of my whole piece with the
old keys, right? and therefore you're
gonna see peaks which are the alignment
of the cosine similarity
whenever you get basically
the audio matching your specific kernel.
so I'm gonna be doing this but with
these specific tones I actually extract
it here. So here I'm going to be showing
you first how the two spectrograms look
like the left side is going to be the
spectrogram of my actual signal X of t
and on the right hand side I have just
the spectrogram of this concatenation of
my pitches, so here you can clearly see
this *makes sound* but then here, first of all, what
are these bars here, these vertical bars?
you following, right? I can't see you, have to
actually talk back. What are these red
bars here, vertical bars? Now, the
horizontal one I already told you, right?
*makes sound* and the vertical? what is
it? sampling issues, right, transitions. So
whenever you have the *makes sound* you actually have
one white waveform one waveform and then
the other one, one waveform has to stop
so it's no longer periodic and whenever
you do a Fourier transform of a non
periodic signal you get you know crap.
That's why whenever you get the
junction between these the *makes sound* the jump
here you're gonna have this spike
because you can
think about the jump is like having a
very high frequency right? because
it's like a delta, so you actually
get all the frequencies, that's why you
get all the frequencies here. Boom. Okay?
makes sense so far? kind of? alright.
So this is the clean version *makes sound* I
cannot even sign and what
left side here? why is on the left-hand
side all red down there? Okay
yes, You knew. so the left side left hand
the cord are the one I show you on the
bottom left side. Okay so let me finish
this class and then I'll let you go. So
here I'm gonna show you
first all the kernels, you can tell now
the red one is going to be the first
chunk of my signal, the real
one and then you can see the first pitch
has the same frequency,
can you see? So the *makes sound*
has the same
delta t the same interval,
period, can you see? you cannot nod your
head because again I don't see you, have
to answer me. Can you see or not? Okay,
thank you, fantastic. And so this one is
that the third one you can see that it
starts here in the period and it
finishes here, if you go up here you're
gonna see exactly there were two of
these guys, right, so that's
how you can see this is like
twice the frequency of the one below.
Finally I'm gonna be performing the
convolution of these four kernels with
my input signal, and this is how we look
like, okay, so the first kernel has a high
match in the first part of the
score. So between zero and zero five
seconds. The second one starts just after
after the first one, then you have the
third one starting at zero three I guess
and then you have the last one
starting at the zero six okay? So
guess what? I'm gonna make you listen to
convolutions now, are you excited?
oh okay, you actually answering now, good!
Alright and so these are the outcomes.
Let me lower a little the volumes
otherwise you will complain, yeah I can't
lower the,
okay, so the first one, let's try again
*plays sound* how cool is that? You listen to
convolutions. Okay so basically this was
almost it, I have one more slide because I
felt like there was some confusion last
time about what is the different
dimensionality of different type of
signals, so I'm really recommending to go
and take the class of Joan Bruna which
is math for deep learning and I stole
one of his, you know, small things he was
teaching, I just put a one slide here
together for you. So this slide is the
following. So we have the input
layer or the samples we provide into
this network and so usually our last
time I define this I have this curly X
which is gonna be made of those x i's
which are all my data samples right
and so I usually have m data
samples so my i goes from m=1 to n, ok, so
is this clear? on is this notation clear?
because it's a bit more formal I'm usually a bit
less formal but then somehow someone was
feeling a little bit not comfortable I
think so this one is just my input
samples but we can also see this one
is this curly X which is my input set as
the set of all these functions as x i's
which are mapping my Omega capital Omega
which is my domain to a RC which are
going to be basically my channels of
that specific example and so here I'm
gonna be mapping those lowercase Omega
to these x i's of omega so let's see how
these different this from the previous
notation. So I'm gonna give you now three
examples and you should be able to
tell now what is the dimensionality and
in this example. So the first one,
let's say,
I have like the one I showed you right now
in the time, just fun piece of you
audio signal, so my Omega is going to be
just the samples like sample number one
sample number two like the index, right?
so you have index one, index two, index
until these 70,000 whatever we just saw
right now, okay? and the last value is
going to be the T, capital T, which is the
number of seconds divided by the delta T
which would be the 1 over the
frequency and this is going to be a
subset of n right? so this is a discrete
number of samples, because you have a
computer, you always have discrete
samples. So this is my input data, and
then what about the image of this
function? so when I ask what is the
dimensionality of this type of signal,
you should answer this is a
one-dimensional signal because the power
of these n here is 1 ok? so this is like
a 1 dimensional signal, although you may
have the total time and the
1 there it was a sampling interval, on
the right hand side you have the number
of channels can be 1 if you have a mono
signal or you can have 2 if you have a
stereophonic, so you have mono there, you
have a 2 for stereophonic or what is 5
plus 1? that's the Dolby like 5.1 how
cool? alright so this is still a one
dimensional signal which may have
multiple channels, nevertheless is still
one dimensional signal because there is
only one running variable there ok? is it
somehow better than last time? yes? no?
better? thank you.
let's say thanks to Joan. Alright, second
example I have here my Omega is going to
be the Cartesian product of these two
sets, the first set is going to be going
from 1 to the height, and also this one
in discrete, and the other one is going
to be going from 1 to the width, so these
are the actual pixels, and so this one
is a 2 dimensional signal because I have
2 degrees of freedom in my
domain. What are the possible channels we
have? So here, the possible channels that
are very very common are the following:
So you can have a grayscale image and
therefore you only output one
scalar value or you get the
rainbow there, the color, and therefore
you get like my X which is a function of
the coordinates Omega 1 Omega 2
which each point is
represented by a vector of three
components which is gonna be the R
component of the point Omega 1 Omega 2,
the G component of Omega 1 Omega 2, and
the blue component of Omega 1 Omega 2. So
again you can all think about this as a
big big data point or you can think
about this as function mapping a low
dimensional domain which is a two
dimensional domain to a three
dimensional domain, right? finally the
twenty, who who knows the name of the
twenty channel image? yeah, this is a
hyperspectral image. It's very common to
have 20 bands.
Finally, who can guess this one?
if my my domain is r4 x r4, what can
it be?
No, no, this discrete right?
This is r4, so it's not even computer. Ha!
who said something there? I heard! Yes
this correct so this is space-time, what
is the second one?
Yeah, which momentum? It has a special
name. It's called four momentum
because it has a temporal information as
well, right?
And so what's gonna be my possible image
of the X function? let's say it's c equals 1.
What is it? do you know?
So this could be for example the
Hamiltonian of the system, okay? so this
was like a bit more mathematical
introduction or mathematical
procedure, how do you say, you'll make
make a more precise definition. So that
was pretty much everything for today, let
me turn on the light and I see you
on next Monday.
Thank you for being with me.